welcome to strength weekly the weekly
YouTube show/ podcast SL whatever you
call it that brings you the inside scoop
of all things strength from around the
barbell
game I'm one of your hosts David Thomas
to and I'm joined by Phil bman this is
brought to you by barbed and we have
lots of strong people breaking World
Records today so stick around but before
we into that make sure you subscribe to
barbend on the
youtube.com anyway we have some intense
stories today including strong people
doing really strong things let's talk
about our run of show first up our
friend and former barbin podcast guest
Rudy cadb it's cool to call him a friend
squats over his IPL world record and
training just doing ridiculous things
we're going to go into what that means
as he nears 75 years of age Andrew House
squats a house and bench presses a
deadlifts houses as well and sets an
all-time raw Squat and total world
records at absolutely stunning
especially given the fact that he's not
even 30 years old yet some of the
biggest records we've seen in
powerlifting in a number of years Jesus
olivz also squats a gargantuan amount of
weight not a world record this was in
training but does it spell the end for
Ray Williams time as the super heavy
squat King and then our final segment
the 2024 CrossFit Game season has been
announced and it looks very different
than any other CrossFit Game season we
have ever seen Phil I ask you this
before we record every time which is
your favorite story to talk about today
you always say David stop asking me that
but I am a bad listener David you are
constantly not listening to me when I
tell you to stop asking me about that
but since you did I got I mean Andrew
how how lucky are we that the day after
it happens we get to record about him
crushing the heaviest weight ever seen
in this weight class I mean if you're
not excited about that I don't know what
will excite you in the strength world
yeah it's also a good reminder that
power power liting has a 38lb category
it is a strength sport where you could
be over 300 lb and not be a super
heavyweight just to put that in
comparison but you know what let's get
into our good friend Rudy Rudy cadb 74
years old he's one of the co-founders of
Kabuki strength in the beautiful Pacific
Northwest and Rudy uh he's got the
Master's categories in the 100 110 kilo
weight categories in a headlock he
absolutely decimates them especially
when it comes to the squat
and the deadlift now Rudy is a good
friend of Barb benthan on our podcast
before one of my favorite episodes he's
well known for doing a shot of whiskey
and deadlifting 500 pounds on his
birthday every year and this time well
he is doing something big but with the
weight on his back not in His Hands
posted a back squat of 2133 kilograms
that's about 470 pounds which is over
his IPL Masters world record of 210
kilograms he's kind of in a class of his
own when it comes to men in this
category squatting nearly 500 lbs at 74
years old uh Phil can you put that in
any perspective for us he's got a lock
pretty much on all of the uh Masters 70
to 74 world records in the lifts that
you mentioned and now that he's getting
up to his 75th birthday he's going to
move into that Masters category and then
dominate all of those records because
all of those records are also less than
what he's currently lifting now so as
long as you know he continues the
trajectory he has of drinking that
whiskey shot and deadlifting on his
birthday every year I think we're going
to see him dominating yet another Divi
another category of Masters World
Records in 2024 we're not saying the
whiskey shot and deadlift is a barbend
approved training regimen but we're not
saying it's not that's that's all I'm
going to say there and he is actually
training for the IPL World Championships
uh which are in just about a week
actually less than a week from this
recording and they're in his backyard
they're in Eugene Oregon so he don't
even have to fly that far I don't think
he has to fly at all I think it's going
to be like a short drive for him
he's lifting what he's currently lifting
in training and he's got to be close to
if not already at body weight for his
category for this competition because
it's so close to that lift that we can
Fair more or less presume that he is
going to call for a world record weight
on the bar and if he converts yet
another world record I mean we shouldn't
be surprised that Rudy is crushing world
record after world record like he
consistently does when he competes but
such such is the case even at 74 he's
stacking him like Lego bricks and one
fun fact that I learned about Rudy on
our podcast he was involved in a
University study where they measured
bone density
of Master's athletes and actually had
basically off the charts world record
bone density for his age weight category
Etc Rudy cadb uh strong guy strong bones
great person and I will make sure to
link the podcast in the show notes below
and also if you are interested in
knowing the correlation between bone
density and resistance training and how
one might affect the other how one might
might may may or may not affect the
other according to the latest research
you can check it out on baron.com Wow we
write everything it's crazy it's almost
like we're a site dedicated to strength
training and strength Sports who would
have thought it a lot of venture
capitalists told me it was a bad idea
back in the day and look where they are
now probably on private islands
somewhere anyway segment two Andrew
House set some alltime World Records in
both the squat and the total in the 308
pound category for powerlifting for raw
this is not raw with refs this is not
equipped this is raw so KN sleeves not
wraps um Phil give us the rundown if you
don't mind because you wrote the article
Andrew he he competed at the 2023 uspc
The Shack Showdown and he squatted 440
kgrs or 970 pounds that's an all-time
world record in the Raw category he
benched pressed 264 kilograms which
actually might have been the most
interesting lift of the entire of his
entire performance even though it wasn't
an all-time world record he deadlifted
387 kilograms and that amounted to a
1,11 kilogram total or 24
24273 pounds an alltime raw world record
so he lifts an all-time squat world
record goes in and misses his first two
bench uh press attempts now if he misses
his third he doesn't claim the record
he's got to complete he's got to post
the total in order for the world records
to count so he goes into his last bench
press and his bench press on his third
one was still heavier than his other two
he never like matched weight on the bar
he continued to go up in weight even
though he missed his first two so him
hitting his third bench press of 264
kilograms to convert his all-time squat
world record I mean the pressure is on
in that lip so I think that his third
bench press is actually the most
impressive lift of the day even though
he scored two World Records it's crazy
it's a really important thing to note pH
I'm glad you pointed it out you need to
post a total for your record to count on
that day one of the reasons is that
people could in theory show up just
focus on one lift kind of not worry
about the others just kind of phone them
in and that's not really fair right
that's not that's a little maybe too
much gamesmanship or kind of taking a
slick route or something like that angle
shooting maybe if you will if you're a
card player and you know that term so
you do need to post a total right you
can't just squat oh set a record on
piecing out that's an all-time world
record in order for this to count in
powerlifting and for most Outlets places
organizations to recognize it you do got
to post that total so it was really do
or die on that third bench press attempt
and I'm sure the adrenaline was at an
all-time high not only for Andrew but in
the room one other thing I want to point
out this dude's got the better part of
four years left in his 20s to add on
strength this is in the sport of
powerlifting a sport where a lot of
folks don't reach full maturity as
competitors until their mid sometimes
late 30s sometimes into their 40s as
we've seen it's all very dependent on
the weight class the lifter Etc really
potentially staking his claim early on
as the most exciting powerlifter
certainly in some of the heavier weight
categories in powerlifting and maybe
already staking his claim as the
greatest 308 of all time and I think
there's also to to reiterate that he
still has weight to give you know I mean
he's posting these numbers and he's not
even at the weight cap the trajectory
for him going forward is just either
more World Records or just advancing on
the list that he doesn't have the world
records in already I mean he did hit a
582 pound bench press I mean that's
crazy I will say that we'll actually
often see people in the heavier weight
classes especially the super heav often
times they won't deadlift the most Inc
competition
because they can't get into the more
optimal body positioning to deadlift
right so leverages might actually be
more advantageous for slightly lighter
athletes another thing that comes up
hands right we have heard from multiple
super heavyweight powerlifters that when
they hit a certain weight category if
they put on too much weight their hands
get too big right they have too much
mass in their hands be that fat be that
muscle and they actually can't grip as
well and you will see if you watch watch
a power lifting competition watch the
Super Heavies because you will see over
the course of a long big power lifting
competition a number of Super Heavies
miss the lift on grip if you stay and
you actually watch I would recommend it
but just note in powerlifting and
something that took me a long time to
start realizing was that it's not often
about maxing out your body weight it's
about coming into the body weight where
your leverages are good where you're
lifting well and you're moving well and
for these bigger heavier athletes those
five kilo differences can make a big
difference in how the body is positioned
under over gripping the barbell all
right let's move into the Super
heavyweight category we will take it up
a notch and we're going to talk about
Jesus olivz squatting 463 kilograms or
about 1,020 pounds give and take raw
training for the 2024 Sheffield
championships now that is not a world
record I want to point out that uh Ray
Williams has the alltime world record
squat raw at 4
77.5 kilograms but this is more of Jesus
I think staking his claim as the best
potential successor to Williams's record
now I want to point out when barbend
first started back in
2016 Ray Williams was the first person
really squatting over a thousand pounds
raw to ipf standards right it had
arguably been done in training in
certain federations but like walking the
barbell out and it made national news
right this was like playing on ESPN and
you could actually see it on television
because it was such a Monumental thing
now you've got multiple athletes pushing
this weight at that standard Phil what
does this training performance indicate
for you about what he might be bringing
to the Sheffield meet in early 2024 the
Sheffield's probably the biggest one of
the biggest uh powerlifting events of
the year the prize purse definitely
supports that and I think that oler is
the defending Champion he's coming back
in he knew he had an invite from last
year when he won it and I think if if he
were to go for a world record and score
it I mean that's the kind of platform
you want to score it on I I would be
surprised if he didn't at least call for
a world record on his third attempt if
not his second if his first one goes
well and he secures it we have watched
him from like the early days when he was
like finding his way in the super
heavyweight division to now where he's a
top guy I think that he is going to at
at least at the very least attempt the
world record if not claim it he did set
the all time total world record at the
Sheffield in 2023 for raw powerlifting
uh it's the rare rare rare feet where he
squatted over a thousand bench press
over 600 and deadlifted over 900 I mean
this this feels like it's oliv Vera's
stage you know like this is his event
he's he's got the experience he's the
defending Champion he knows that he can
he knows that he can lift these weights
right like we're seeing it in training
like it's not like he's going to have to
go for Brook he's going to know what his
range is you know yeah Phil do you know
what I can do with 410 kilograms David
please enlighten us absolutely nothing
anyway on that's a lot to do there a lot
to do with 4 I can I can look at it I
can give it a hard stare all right onto
our final segment of the day not
powerlifting CrossFit so if you're a
powerlifter stick around because this
segment might make you feel stronger but
potentially winded by comparison we now
have details and dates for most of most
of the 2024 CrossFit Game season we will
no longer have the championships for the
age group and adaptive division so
that's the teens the Masters and the
adapted divisions those will no longer
be contested at the CrossFit Games it's
the first time we've seen that in a long
time now one thing I will say to
crossfits credit when you add up the
number of Divisions between teens
Masters and adaptive athletes there is
so much content and the way the CrossFit
games has been set up in the past a lot
of these had to run simultaneously right
these divisions had to run different
events simultaneously somewhere in like
the Coliseum some were out on the fields
some were on Trails or whatever in the
water it's a Monumental like Olympic
game size lift to broadcast all of these
things and to be perfectly honest we
don't see the Olympic Games broadcast
everything live and that's the Olympics
across all those Sports so just to keep
that in mind Phil when does the CrossFit
Game season kick off next year the
CrossFit Games officially kicks off on
Thursday February 29th with workout 24.1
of the CrossFit open now similar to last
year there's going to be three workouts
that comprise the open before we go into
the quarterfinals and then the
semi-finals and then we actually get to
the games so that that trajectory of how
to get to the games to qualify is still
there but as you mentioned the
differences between where the Masters
and teens and adaptiv Visions will go is
not at the games they will have their
own events in a different location and I
agree I think that logistically speaking
even though it may have stung when first
realizing oh these are going to be
separate events I think the amount of
coverage that they're going to get to
actually highlight the quality of
athletes in these divisions is going to
be for the better because they will
actually be able to diversify how much
they can how much time they can allocate
to their coverage for each division yeah
and also more ma more athletes are
actually going to be able to compete at
these championships it's worth noting
that this actually expands the number of
athletes who are going to be able to
compete in age group at adaptive um
championships but all athletes all
athletes start at the open and I'm just
going to read some stats the top 25% of
individuals it was formerly top 10% and
teams in each region will advance to the
quarterfinals and the top 25% of each
age group from every region will advance
to uh the quarterfinals as well so it is
worth noting the open is still the
feeder for all of these right we still
have the open we still have
quarterfinals we still have semi
semi-finals we just won't see H grp and
adaptive athletes at the CrossFit Games
the top 10 adaptive athletes from 15
divisions will advance from the Adaptive
CrossFit semi-final by wheel wad to the
Adaptive CrossFit Games by wheel wad now
the competition dates and location for
that TBD we actually don't know yet same
with the age groups now Masters and
teens are going to be different the top
masters from the AG group semi-final
will advance to the Masters CrossFit
Games presented by Legends we don't know
the date and location yet and then the
top 30 boys and 30 girls from the
Teenage divisions will advance from the
semi-finals to the teenage CrossFit
Games by the pit team Throwdown we do
know where that is Three Rivers Michigan
we just don't know the dates yet however
we do know the dates for the CrossFit
games where you will see individual and
team competitions go down to determine
the fittest on Earth Phil give us the
dates and location because it's new this
year yeah the CrossFit games are leaving
Madison Wisconsin they've been there for
the last couple of years but this year
they're going to be in Fort Worth Texas
and it's going to take place from August
8th through the 11th 2024 which means
that it still will be hot you are not
you are not escaping a hot environment
watching these uh Elite athletes run
wearing their Ruck socks and you know
Farmers walking their giant kettle bells
yeah it's about a week later and a lot
further south in Madison and here's the
thing a lot of folks thought that when
the CrossFit Games moved from California
to Madison they were like oh it's not
going to be as hot I've been on the
ground for the CrossFit Games in Madison
it's super super hot and doing the
CrossFit Games in Madison in July ju was
very hot I do have news for all the
athletes hosting the CrossFit Games in
August in Texas is also going to be
extremely hot I'm not sure what the
mosquito situation is because it was
pretty bad in Madison we'll see how it
is in Fort Worth Texas Phil have you
ever been to Fort Worth I have and I I
haven't been in the middle of August
though and I know that when it's that
kind of heat in at that time with the
amount of events that the uh individuals
and teams are going to have to do the
way that you might perform in the gym or
way that you might perform where you're
not bearing down that kind of heat over
a 5-day competition like the temperature
will play a role and I'm sure the you
know top athletes their coaches and
everything are are figuring out how to
actually Prime them for that but the
Heat plays a role and it's not something
that we necessarily uh see translated
through coverage yeah and we we do see
athletes basically acclimating and being
on location weeks ahead of time at this
point oftentimes to adapt to the heat
training conditions environment Etc get
their diets locked in make sure they're
comfortable where they're sleeping not
the sort of thing where you can expect
to fly and day of and be at your
absolute best so a lot of athletes kind
of set up mini camps or the coaches will
set up mini camps for the athletes
actually on location leading up to the
games well it's a CrossFit Game season
unlike any we've ever seen and that
brings us to the end of today's show for
Barb ben.com I'm David Thomas to who the
heck are you I am Phil Blackman senior
editor of Barb ben.com thank you all for
watching this episode of strength weekly
and we will catch you next time
appreciate it
folks